Finding Aid for First United Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.) records, 1829-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First United Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.) records 1829-1979
First United Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
86931 Ba 2
Presbyterian church established in Ypsilanti, Michigan in 1829; Church registers, session minutes; records of woman's missionary society and ladies aid society; records, 1906-1940, of board of trustees; and records, 1830-1846, of the First Congregational Society.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church (donor no. 1305 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The First Presbyterian Church of Ypsilanti traces its history back to 1829 when the Rev. William Page organized a group of twelve people who formed the nucleus of what would become the First Presbyterian Church. In 1830, a religious society was organized with the name First Congregational Society of Ypsilanti. In 1832, there was discussion whether the government of this new church would follow a Presbyterian or Congregational model. The members elected to adopt the Presbyterian form and the church was formally known as the First Presbyterian Church of Ypsilanti. From its founding, the church had included a few Congregationalists. As there numbers grew, a demand arose for a distinct Congregational organization. That organization took effect October 4, 1881 with the Congregationalists forming a separate First Congregational Society of Ypsilanti. The division of the church was made amicably.
The record group includes registers containing record of baptisms, marriages, and membership. In addition, there are early record books of the church, including session minutes. Many of the records relate to groups within the church, especially the Woman's Missionary Society and the Ladies Aid Society. The remainder of the record group is comprised of miscellaneous early documents, history and background information, and a scattering of photographs.
Subjects:
First Congregational Society (Ypsilanti, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); First United Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Congregational churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Women--Michigan--Ypsilanti--Societies and clubs.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; First United Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Presbyterian churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Churches.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Registers of members, baptisms, marriages, etc.
  - 1829-1956, 6 volumes (Box 1)
    (Microfilm copy available in part)
- Governance
  - Record book of the First Congregational Society 1830-1846 (Box 1)
  - Record book 1832-1843, original and typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Session minutes
    - 1835-1850 (Box 1)
      (there were pages torn out at beginning and end of volume probably covered the missing period of 1829-1834 and 1851-1855)
    - 1856-1872 (Box 2)
    - 1872-1899 (Box 2)
    - 1899-1913 (Box 2)
    - 1913-1924 (Box 2)
    - 1924-1944 (Box 2)
    - 1944-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1975 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees Record book 1906-1940 (Box 3)
- Church Groups
  - Westminster Guild record book 1911-1921 (Box 3)
  - Home Workers of the Presbyterian Church record book 1882-1883 (Box 3)
  - Woman's Missionary Society record books
    - 1869-1874 (Box 3)
    - 1875-1881 (Box 3)
    - 1827-1935 (Box 3)
    - 1944-1950 (Box 3)
  - Ladies Aid Society
    - Record books
      - 1893-1900 (Box 3)
      - 1900-1905 (Box 3)
      - 1902-1904 (Box 3)
      - 1906-1911 (Box 3)
      - 1911-1915 (Box 3)
      - 1927-1933 (Box 3)
    - Constitution (Box 3)
    - General correspondence (Box 3)
    - Annual reports 1900, 1905, 1906, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Financial reports (Box 3)
- Early documents
  (includes both First Presbyterian and First Congregational documents)
  - Admissions and dismissions (Box 4)
  - Bills and statements 1833-1842 (Box 4)
  - Calls (Box 4)
  - Certificates of election of trustees 1831-1844 (Box 4)
  - Contract for building of Church 1856 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
  - Deeds for pews 1836 (Box 4)
  - Financial reports (Box 4)
  - Financial statements 1835-1845, undated (Box 4)
  - Letters 1839-1843 (Box 4)
  - Meeting house documents 1832-1834, undated (Box 4)
  - Memorial resolution for Jacob Bacon (Box 4)
  - Minutes 1847, 1862 (Box 4)
    (loose sheets; fragments)
  - Miscellaneous 1863-1948 (Box 4)
  - Receipts 1833-1845 (Box 4)
  - Receipts 1860s-1870s (Box 4)
  - Session business 1838-1844 (Box 4)
  - Subscription lists 1833-1845 (Box 4)
  - Sunday School constitution, by-laws and general working plan (Box 4)
  - Sunday School miscellaneous 1877-1880 (Box 4)
  - Trials and confessions (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Directory, annual report, and newsletters 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - History of the Church (Box 4)
    (incomplete)
  - History: Source material for history (Box 4)
  - Memorial windows description (Box 4)
  - Sesquicentennial file (Box 4)
    (minutes of sesquicentennial committee; tape of celebration; and sesquicentennial memory book)
  - Photographs